This one's a bit of a mystery. I had to
go back to the drawing board because as
I finished off analyzing five studies on
the plaque-reversing effects of a tomato
molecule called lycopene, I thought it
was going to be an open-and-shut case.
But I was genuinely puzzled by the
sudden turn of events when I discovered
two more studies causing pause to an
otherwise straightforward benefit of
lycopene. So, I'd like to walk you
through what I discovered, put all the
cards out on the table, and then let you
decide how to think about lycopene in
your own life. Is it something that
you'd consider? I think an argument
could be made for many, though maybe not
all. Lycopene is an antioxidant. So, a
molecule that hunts down and neutralizes
damaging oxidizing molecules called free
radicals. As we go about our lives,
especially if we choose less than ideal
health habits, smoking, overweight gain,
and so on, our body produces more and
more of these destructive molecules,
these free radicals. In the context of
atherosclerosis, the buildup of plaque
in our artery wall, that plays a role
because the plaque is largely made up of
cholesterol-containing particles, and
these particles remain trapped in the
arterial wall if they are oxidized.
Anyway, could lycopene have a role in
those mechanisms? Possibly, but that's
not what we're interested in, really.
We're interested in understanding the
clinical measurements, the actual
removal of plaque out of the blood
vessel, plaque regression.
And it turns out that the tomato-based
lycopene has a lot of evidence in its
favor, indicating that it may just do
exactly that.
All the studies that I just threw on
screen agree that if your blood lycopene
levels are elevated, there's an inverse
relationship with arterial plaque,
meaning that less is present. We can see
that here as just one example. Those
dots are individual data for people that
have had their arterial plaque measured,
indicated by the IMT or the on the
vertical axis. Further up is worse, and
the blood levels of lycopene on the
horizontal axis, greater levels to the
right. So, you see what I mean by an
inverse relationship. If lycopene levels
are low, the line is higher up on the
plaque. And if lycopene is greater
then plaque levels are reduced. Now,
this and the three other studies is just
an association, though. And although the
researchers tried to account for
potential influencing factors, we can't
get past that this is associative. We'll
return to this, but for now, we know
across multiple studies that if your
blood levels of lycopene are high,
meaning more lycopene molecules are
circulating through your blood, there's
generally an association with reduced
plaque in the arteries.
Okay, I think we can agree that's not a
bad start. But the beauty of looking at
things like IMT, which stands for
intima-media thickness, which is useless
to 80% of you, so that stands for plaque
in the arteries, is that plaque
progression and regression can be
measured over months instead of having
to wait years. As a result, we don't
need to rely on silly associations,
those silly silly associations. So cute,
but weak compared to the almighty
randomized controlled trial.
Anyway, there are some trials where
people are given lycopene supplements,
and before supplementation,
have their arterial plaque measured, and
then their plaque is measured again
after being on lycopene for a time. Then
we can directly assess if there's a real
causative effect of lycopene. So, let me
simplify this. I'll move out of the way.
Here's this study,
and then here's this study. And on the
count of three, we will reveal the
results.
One,
two,
three.
That's right. They go in completely
opposite directions. Oh, and what if I
threw into the mix another one of those
silly associative studies and mentioned
that they also found no association
between lycopene and better
cardiovascular health?
Yeah, right about now, you are where I
was when I first ran into these
conflicting studies. I seriously found
the first five studies all agreeing,
happily holding hands, skipping about,
AND THEN SLAM! These two new studies
came in and destroyed the peaceful
harmony that was.
The next step here is to get into the
differences between these studies and
try to find some through lines that can
explain the differences in perspective.
Well, the one associative study that
disagrees with the rest is
methodologically the more sound study
over all four previous ones. It's much
larger, the way the data is collected is
typically higher quality, the controls
for outside influencing factors are
better and more. So,
do we crown it above the rest
automatically?
Well, typically, yes. But in this case,
probably not. Why?
Because
the researchers themselves pointed out
that they looked for the association
between dietary lycopene and
cardiovascular health. That's fine.
Except when they went to validate the
dietary lycopene to blood values, they
found weak associations. That means that
the dietary recall for lycopene may have
been poor due to measurement error. That
throws out a serious wrench into making
any strong conclusions based on this
study. Now, I'll return to this study in
a moment because there's something else
important related to it. Okay, then. We
can return to our two randomized
controlled trials. One did not measure
plaque itself, but did assess many heart
disease risk factors like blood
pressure, blood cholesterol levels,
insulin resistance, inflammation, and
more. Now, none of those metrics
improved. The other directly measured
plaque burden in the arterial wall, and
that was the one that found an effect.
So, it might seem obvious just to go
with the one that directly tests
clinical measurements, right? Well,
maybe. But I think there's a bit more
context to understand, like the pairing
of an additional nutrient with lycopene.
Now, before I touch on all that, you may
be interested in having a list of
independently verified lycopene
supplements or a deeper analysis of the
lycopene-cardiovascular disease
relationship, or some sex-based
differences. As always, I'm covering
that plus more in my extended edition of
this analysis, which is available for
the Physionic Insiders, which includes a
more in-depth video and accompanying
article plus access to my master list of
supplements, including dosing
considerations, disease categorizations,
reputable sources, and if the supplement
is worthwhile.
Oh, and yes, all of these perks right
here. Podcast, live session, private
community, and more. Anyway, the link to
join the Physionic Insiders is in the
description. I hope to see you there.
So, let's get into these a bit,
especially this study that did find an
effect. The thing is, this trial did
some unique things. One, it paired
lycopene with a prominent eye supplement
called lutein. Here, we see all three
groups, and we're measuring the same
plaque in the arteries. The higher the
bars, the more plaque in our arteries, a
bad thing. Now, the white bars are
before the study, and the hash, the
darker bars, are after each condition.
So, lutein alone or lutein plus
lycopene. As you can tell, lutein alone
was effective, but what was even more
effective was the combination treatment.
Now, there are two major reasons this
study may have shown an effect related
to cardiovascular cardiovascular health
while the other didn't.
One, the previous study, even the
researchers brought up that their
participants may have been too healthy.
Don't you hate it when people are just
too healthy?
Who do they think they are? We need them
to be guinea pigs in our science
experiments, and they just end up being
too healthy. Just so damn selfish.
Anyway, I'm not sure if I buy it or not
because, well, yes, they were healthier
than the people in the study that we
just went over, they still weren't
symbols of perfect health, either. The
second reason is that the study showing
the effect lasted a full year, while the
study indicating no effect only lasted a
few months. So, yes, it's possible both
could contribute to these divergent
results. At this point,
you'd have to make a choice on if this
evidence is strong enough in your mind
to warrant pursuing lycopene to help
against your cardiovascular disease.
Ultimately, this is how I'd approach it.
I honestly don't think that the evidence
is strong for lycopene. The evidence in
favor is weak, even if there are several
studies,
and in any case, we need more data,
preferably randomized controlled trials,
to make a strong case one way or
another. However,
what data we do have shyly
points to doses of lycopene around 20 mg
or higher per day possibly having an
effect, if an effect is to be found.
Now, if that's through supplement
supplementation or through tomato-based
foods, that's completely up to you. And
in fact, if you wanted to get a
therapeutic dose through tomato-based
foods, it's doable, though the amounts
vary, ranging from 1 mg up to 7 mg per
100 g of tomato. Funny enough, processed
tomatoes, like in paste, actually supply
more, anywhere from 10 to 30 mg per 100
g,
depending on the product. And like I
promised earlier,
we'd return, albeit briefly, to this
naysaying associative study. Though they
did not find any positive link between
lycopene and cardiovascular health, they
did find some evidence that tomato-based
foods had a healthful link to
cardiovascular system health. So,
that might be because the tomatoes
contain more than just lycopene. Look,
ultimately, if you don't have a history
of cardiovascular disease, don't worry
about lycopene. It isn't worth it based
on the evidence that we have now. If you
do have a history of cardiovascular
disease, even then, it'll be up to you
if it's worthwhile for you. Some of you
may think, "Yes, so long that I take it
at the correct dose and over the correct
length of time." And others will think,
"Nah,
there are more potent nutrients and
habits that will give me a bigger bang
for my buck." And speaking to that last
stance, I have covered more potent ways
of improving your cardiovascular health
more than strong science right here.
Thanks for tuning in. Hope this helped.
Catch you in the next one. See you.